Finding aid to the Black Students Alliance records CA.MS.00308
Smith College Archives
Black Students Alliance records
1969-2009
Smith College Archives
Black Students Alliance
CA.MS.00308
5.0 linear feet (13 containers and 2 poster boards)
This collection contains notebooks, correspondence, conference materials, minutes, photographs, and event fliers documenting the Black Students Alliance.
Biographical / Historical
The earliest records of the Black Students Alliance (BSA) date from 1970, when black students and faculty across the Five Colleges formed a committee to demand the inclusion of Afro-American Studies in Five College curriculums. Smith's BSA became active soon afterward, first with protests concerning the state of Afro-American Studies at Smith and then with student newsletters and events. In 1974 the BSA ran a children's fair at the Mwangi Cultural Center, then located in Lily Hall. The goal of the fair was to educate local children about black cultural heritage. The BSA's annual events have included a Black Arts Festival, Black History Observance events, cultural events such as Kwanza and musical performers, social events including parties and movie nights for both BSA members and the larger campus community. The BSA has also participated regularly in local black students' conferences. Additionally, the BSA has been partially in charge of Unity House and the Mwangi Cultural Center with the cultural center staff since its creation in the 1970s, and an active participant in planning and running Bridge, an annual pre-orientation program for students of color.
Scope and Contents
The records of the BSA include general and officers' notebooks which contain a variety of materials, including notes, minutes, correspondence, budget sheets, event fliers, reports, and more.
The records also contain files of minutes and correspondence concerning the Mwangi Cultural Center, the Five College Executive Committee on Afro-American Studies, Smith College's Afro-American Studies Department, and the annual black student's conference. There are also a few files of BSA newsletters and other assorted correspondence.
Most of the photographs are unidentified and undated. They are mainly of various BSA members and events.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into thirteen series:
I. HISTORY
II. NOTEBOOKS
III. MWANGI CULTURAL CENTER
IV. AFRO-AMERICAN STUDIES DEPARTMENT
V. 5-COLLEGE AND INTERCOLLEGIATE
VI.CONFERENCE MATERIALS
VII. NEWSLETTERS
VIII. EVENTS
IX. GENERAL FILES, A - Z
X. CLIPPINGS
XI. POETRY AND LYRICS
XII. PHOTOGRAPHS
XIII. ARTIFACTS
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The records of the Black Students Alliance were donated over a period of time to the Smith College Archives from a variety of sources.
- Series I. History
  - Charter, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Constitution, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Our Firsts" - a history of students' racial diversity at Smith College, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Series II. Notebooks
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1981-82; undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Executive Board Minutes, 1997-98 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Executive Board Minutes, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Executive Board Members, 1985-86 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Chair's Notebook (2 folders), 1996-97 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Chair's Notebook, 1998-99 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chair's Notebook (5 folders), 2002-03 (Box 1, Folder 11-15)
  - Chair's Notebook (12 folders), 2003-04 (Box 1, Folder 16-27)
  - Vice Chair's Notebook (6 folders), 1998-99 (Box 2, Folder 1-6)
  - Vice Chair's Notebook (7 folders), 1999-2000 (Box 2, Folder 7-13)
  - Vice Chair's Notebook (7 folders), 2004-05 (Box 2, Folder 14-20)
  - Vice Chair's Notebook (1-2 of 7 folders), 2006-07 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
  - Vice Chair's Notebook (3-7 of 7 folders), 2006-07 (Box 3, Folder 1-5)
  - Secretary's Notebook (2 folders), 1998-99 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
  - Treasurer's Notebook, 1991-92 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Treasurer's Notebook (8 folders), 1998-99 (Box 3, Folder 9-16)
  - Treasurer's Notebook (1-6 of 10 folders), 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 17-22)
  - Treasurer's Notebook (7-10 of 10 folders), 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  - Treasurer's Notebook (9 folders), 2000-01 (Box 4, Folder 5-13)
  - Treasurer's Notebook (1-5 of 10 folders), 2002-06 (Box 4, Folder 14-18)
  - Treasurer's Notebook (6-10 of 10 folders), 2005-06 (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
  - Treasurer's Notebook (2 folders), 2006-07 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
  - Social Chair's Notebook (6 folders), 2000-01 (Box 5, Folder 8-13)
  - Social Chair's Notebook (1-5 of 10 folders), 2005-06 (Box 5, Folder 14-18)
  - Social Chair's Notebook (6-10 of 10 folders), 2005-06 (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
  - Club Notebook (3 folders), 1989-90 (Box 6, Folder 6-8)
  - Club Notebook (11 folders), 1996-98 (Box 6, Folder 9-19)
  - Club Notebook, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Club Notebook, 2005-06 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Club Notebook, 2007-08 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Black History Observance Committee Notebook, 1983-84 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Ticket Seller's Notebook, 1996-97 (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Series III. Mwangi Cultural Center
  - History, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - General information, 1973; undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Activities and events, 1972-73; 1996-97; 2002-05 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Closing/Rededication Ceremony, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Dr. Mwangi Ng'endo, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Students, 1980-82 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Reports, 1975; 1979 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Space use agreements, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Space use agreements, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Smith College Space Utilization Study, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Staff minutes and correspondence, 1980-81 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Unity Leader Training Notebook (4 folders), 1999-2000 (Box 7, Folder 14-18)
- Series IV. Afro-American Studies Department
  - History, undated (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Brochures and information packet, 1970; 1982-83; undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Clarification of Demands for the Department, 1971 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence with President Mendenhall, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence re: survey from Afro-American Studies Advisory Committee, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Memo: Goals for the Department, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Proposed Interdepartmental Major report, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 25)
- Series V. 5-College and Intercollegiate
  - Correspondence: Wellesley College Black Students Union, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence: 5-College Presidents, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - Interim 5-College Executive Committee on Afro-American Studies Meeting Minutes (2 folders), 1970-74 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - Smith-Amherst Tutorial Proposal, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - "A Proposal for the W.E.B. Du Bois Department of Afro-American Studies (UMASS)", 1970 (Box 7, Folder 30)
- Series VI. Conference Materials
  - Correspondence, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - Schedule, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - Suggestions, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Board Information, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence (1-4 of 6 folders), 2005-06 (Box 7, Folder 35-38)
  - Correspondence (5-6 of 6 folders), 2005-06 (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - Checklists, 2005-06 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Financial Records, 2005-06 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Fundraising, 2005-06 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 2005-06 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Notebook (3 folders), 2006 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Panelist Information, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Panel Questions, 2005-06 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Publicity, 2005-06 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Reference: "Getting Real: Black Women Taking Charge in the Fight Against AIDS", undated (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Registration forms (3 folders), 2006 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Schedule, 2006 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Notebook (2 folders), 2008-09 (Box 8, Folder 14)
- Series VII. Newsletters
  - Newsletter, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Newsletters, 1983-84 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Newsletters, 1991-92 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Newsletters, 1998-99 (Box 8, Folder 18)
- Series VIII. Events
  - Black Arts Festival: general, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Black Arts Festival 1978 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Black Arts Festival 1980, 1979-80 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Black Arts Festival 1981, 1980-81 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Black Arts Festival 1982, 1981-82 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Black Arts Festival 1983, 1982-83 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Black Arts Festival 1984 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Black Arts Festival 1985, 1984-85 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Black Arts Festival 1986, 1985-86 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Black Arts Festival 1987, 1986-87 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Black Arts Festival 1999 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Bridge: Pre-orientation program for students of color. See also DVD088-DVD091., 1992; 2002; 2004; 2007 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Children's Fair, 1984-85 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Children's Workshop, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Cultural Expansions, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Family Weekend - Ada Comstock Women of Color, 2009 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Howard University Concert Choir [See V442], Spring 2002 (Box 9)
  - Karma Weekend, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Kwanza, 1983-88; 1998-2008 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Ndguda Fashion Show, 1971 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Otelia Cromwell Day, 1981-89; 1996-97; 2005 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Spring Black Festival, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - General, 1979-80 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - General, 1982-83 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - General, 1984-85 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - General, 1985-86 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - General, 1994-95 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - General, 1995-96 (Box 9, Folder 27)
  - General, 1997-98 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - General, 1998-99 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - General, 1999-2000 (Box 9, Folder 30)
  - General, 2000-01 (Box 9, Folder 31)
  - General, 2001-02 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - General, 2004-05 (Box 9, Folder 33)
  - General, 2005-06 (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - General, 2006-07 (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - General, 2007-08 (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - General, 2008-09 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - General, 2009-10 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - General, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Series IX. General Files, A-Z
  - Black Alumnae Newsletter, 1983; 2006 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Black Alumnae Weekend, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Black Face, 2007-08 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Black United Front, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Budget Allocation, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Budget Allocation, 1986-87 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Budget Allocation, 1990-91 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Car Use Forms and Guidelines, 1985 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence - general, 1978-86 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence - general, 1992 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence - general, 2005-09 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence - BSA members, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence - President Dunn, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence - The Engravery, undated (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence - Smith College student body, 1981; 1990 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence - Speak Out! Internship Opportunities, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Dennis Brutus Defense, 1981 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Diplomas from engraved holders, undated (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Election Speech Notes (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Entertainment Brochures (2 folders), 1974-2000; undated (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - First years letters, 1973 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Funding request to SGA, 1996 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Guest book, 1993-5; undated (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Hampshire College Course Guide Supplement, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - History of Black Protest at Smith: A study in inevitable conflict…, 1972 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - "I have a dream…" Martin Luther King, Jr Memorial, 1986 (Box 11, Folder 26)
  - Information booklet on BSA, 2005-06 (Box 11, Folder 27)
  - Jewish Women's Studies: An Introductory Bibliography, undated (Box 11, Folder 28)
  - Letterhead, undated (Box 11, Folder 29)
  - "Mathematics Performance Amongst Black Students at the University of California, Berkeley", 1985 (Box 11, Folder 30)
  - Multicultural Development Report, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 31)
  - Nguzo Saba Testimonials and Mshumaa Lighting, undated (Box 11, Folder 32)
  - An Open Letter to My Sister - anonymous, undated (Box 11, Folder 33)
  - R.A.C.E. charter, 1970-71 (Box 11, Folder 34)
  - Racist notes report, 1993 (Box 11, Folder 35)
  - Speech to BSA by Monique Spyke, 2001-02 (Box 11, Folder 36)
  - St. John's Congregational Church Bulletin, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 37)
  - Survey responses, 2005 (Box 11, Folder 38)
- Series X. Clippings
  - Black arts clippings, 1992-98 (Box 11, Folder 39)
  - Smith College clippings, 1987; 1999-2007; undated (Box 11, Folder 40)
  - Smith and the Media booklet, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 41)
- Series XI. Poetry and Lyrics
  - Audre Lorde - "Coal", undated (Box 11, Folder 42)
  - Queen Latifah - "U.N.I.T.Y.", undated (Box 11, Folder 43)
  - Anonymous - "Ebonics Tectonics", undated (Box 11, Folder 44)
- Series XII. Photographs
  - General (7 envelopes), 1969-96 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous (97 envelopes), undated (Box 12, Folder 2-7)
  - Celebration (4 envelopes), undated (Box 12, Folder 8)
- Series XIII. Artifacts
  - 3 engraved diploma holders, 1993 (Box 13)
  - 8 graduation sashes, 2002; 2005-06; 2009 (Box 13)
  - Award medal decorated with diploma and cap, undated (Box 13)
- Oversized Material
  - Posterboard with photos of Rosa Parks, undated (Mapcase FF 15)
  - Posterboard for Kaleidoscope of Color: Portraits of Smith Students of Color, with introduction by BSA Black Culture Chair 1995-96, 1996 (Mapcase FF 15)